In the previous segment, we talked about
how to solve modular linear equations.
上一节我们已经讨论了如何解模块方程组
这一节我们讨论一下如何解模块二次方程组
In this segment, we're gonna talk about how
to solve modular quadratic equations.
通俗一点讲，就是计算模块的e次根，我说过
And more generally, we're gonna talk about how
to compute modular e'th roots. As I said,
我们已经知道如何解模块线性方程组，通过用一个相反的算法
now we know how to solve linear equations
simply by using an inversion algorithm to
计算出的倒数之后与-B相乘。那么现在的问题是
compute a inverse and then multiplying
the result by minus B. So the question is
what about higher degree polynomials and
in particular we are interested in
更高次的多项式，在解方程时尤其关注的是
solving, polynomials modulo primes. So
solving polynomials in ZP, but polynomials
多项式模初始值的运算。所以解Zp中的多项式时，例如Zp
particularly of the form x squared - c
or y cubed - c or z to the 37 - c, all in ZP.
这种形式：x平方-c，或者y的立方-c或者z的37次方-c
So solving this polynomial, for
example, involved computing the square root of C.
例如在解这个方程时涉及计算c的平方根
Solving this polynomial
involves computing the cube root of C.
解这个方程涉及解c的立方根
Solving this polynomial involves computing
the thirty-seventh root of C. And so on.
这个方程要解c的37次根。等等
下来我们设一个初值p，c是Zp的某一个元素
So, again, let's fix the primes P, and
let's say that C is some element in ZP.
我们说Zp中的x满足x^e等于c，我们称
We'll say that X in ZP that satisfies X to
the E is equal to C. We'll call such an X
x是c的e次方根，让我们看一个例子。
the modular E-th root of C. So let's look
at an example. We say that the cube root
在Z11中三次根号下7等于6，因为6的立方等于216
of 7 in Z11 is equal to 6,
because 6 cubed is equal to 216, which
它恰好是7模11。因此7的立方根模11等于6
happens to be 7 modulo 11. And
therefore, the cube root of 7 modulo 11
那么我问一下，在Z11中3的平方根是多少？
is equal to 6. So let me ask you,
what is the square root of 3 in Z11?
答案是5，因为5的平方等于25，刚好是3模11
So the answer is 5 because 5
squared is equal to 25, which is 3 modulo 11.
同样的，三次根号下1模11是多少
And similarly, let me ask
you, what is the cubed root of 1, modulo 11.
1模11的立方根是1，因为1的立方是1.
Well the cube root of 1
is simply 1, because one cubed is equal to 1, in Z11.
实际上，模任何一个初值都是正确的。有一个问题我想指出来的是
In fact that's true
in modulo any prime. One thing I'd like to
这些e次根不是都存在的。例如
point out is that these e'th roots
don't always exist. For example, if I
如果我让你计算二次根号下2模11的值，你将有一个问题
asked you to compute the square root of
2 modulo 11, you'd have a problem,
因为2的平方根模11不存在。
because the square root of two simply
doesn't exist modulo 11. So now that
现在我们明白e次跟是什么了，下一个问题就是这些e次根什么时候
we understand what an e'th root is, the next
question is, when do these e'th roots
存在，并且知道在什么时候存在，我们能不能高效地把他们算出来
exist, and when we know that they do
exist, can we actually compute them efficiently?
所以让 我们开始这个简单的话题。这个话题是
So, let's start with the easy
case. The easy case is, when we want to
当我们想计算一个数的e次根时，并且恰巧e和p-1是互素的
compute an e'th root of something, and it
so happens that e is relatively prime to p-1.
在这种情况下，c的1/e次方是存在的，并且也有一个简单的
In this case, c to the one over
e always exists, and there's a very easy
算法计算出c的e次根和Zp，所以让我们看一下它是如何工作的
algorithm to actually compute the e'th root
of c and ZP. So let's see how this works.
首先，因为e和p-1是互素的，并且知道e的倒数存在
So first, since e is relatively prime to
p-1, we know that e has an inverse
所以让我们计算这个倒数，令倒数等于d
modulo of p-1. So let's compute
this inverse, and let's call it d.
我们让d等于e的倒数模P-1之后我想声明一下实际上c的1/e次方就是c的d次方模p
So let's let d be the inverse of e modulo p-1. Then I claim that in fact c to the 1/e
所以如果这个等式成立那么
is simply c to the d,
modulo p. So if this equation holds then
首先它证明了 对于所有的在Zp中的c它的e次根都存在
first of all it proves that for all
N in ZP the e'th root to c actually
更进一步，它给出了一个有效的算法来计算e次根
exists. And moreover, it gives a very
efficient algorithm to compute this e'th root to c,
通过计算e的倒数模p-1，并且将c提高到倒数的次方
simply by computing the inverse
of e modulo p-1, and then raising
明白了吗？我们就有了一石二鸟之计。
c to the power of that inverse. Okay? So
we kill two birds in one stone. So let's
让我们看一下为什么这个等式成立。首先d倍的e等于
see why this equation holds. So first of
all the fact that d times e is equal to
1模p-1的事实意味着存在某个整数k.这样的话，如果我认为
one mod p-1, what that means is there
exists some integer k. Such that if I look
d倍的e实际就是p倍的（p-1）再加1，
at d times e for that's basically gonna be
k times p-1 plus 1. That's basically
这个的意思是d倍的e等于1模p-1.好的，现在我们可以
what it means that d times e is equal to
one modulo p-1. Well, so now we can
准确的证实了c的d次方是c的一个e次方根
actually confirm that c to the d is a
e'th root of C. Well, how do we
我们怎样证实它呢？让我们取c的d次方的e次方
confirm that? Well, let's take C to the D,
and raise it to the power of E. If in
实际上当我们把它再升到e次方时，c的d次方是c的一个e次方根
fact, c to the d is an e'th root of
c, when we raise it to the power of e;
我们应该返回一个c。让我们来看看这为什么是正确的。那个仅仅等于
we're supposed to get c back. So let's see
why that's true. Well, that's simply equal
c倍的d的e次方，c倍的d的e次方，根据定义等于
to c times d to the e, and c times d to
the e, well, by definition, is equal to c
c的k乘p-1再加1的次方。好的，用这个指数定律，
to the power of k times p-1 plus 1
Well, using the laws of
我们可以写出c的p-1次方的k乘c
exponentiation, we can write this as c to
the power of p-1 to the power of k times c.
我做的这些都是用标准的指数定律分配指数的
All I did is I distributed the
exponentiation using the standard laws of exponentiation.
Now what do we know about
c to the p-1? Since c lives in ZP
现在我们知道c的p-1次方了吗？因为c属于Zp
by Fermat's theorem we know that c
to the p-1 is equal to 1, in ZP.
根据费马定理我们知道c的p-1次方等于1，
1 to the k is also equal to 1 and as a
result, this is simply equal to c in ZP,
1的k次方也等于1因此，这个就等于1模p
which is exactly what we needed to prove
that c to the d is an e'th root of c.
这就是我们需要证明的c的d次方是c的一个e次方根
Okay. So this is what I call the easy
case. In fact, the e'th root always exists
好的，这就是我说的简单事例。实际，e次根通常是存在的
when e is relatively prime to p-1. And it's very easy to compute it
当e与p-1是互素的时候。并且用这里的等式很容易计算出
simply by using this formula here. Now
let's turn to the less easy case. So the
现在我们转向另一个更简单的例子
less easy case is when e is not relatively
prime to p-1. And the canonical example
这个简单的例子是当e与p-1不互素时，这里的例子是
here is when e is equal to 2. So now
suppose we want to compute square roots of
当e等于2时。现在假设我们想计算在Zp中的c的平方根
c in ZP. So if p is an odd prime, and in
fact we are going to focus on odd primes
如果p是奇数，实际从现在开始我们关注的是奇数值
from now on, then in fact p-1 is going to
be even. Which means that two are divided
则p-1是偶数。意味着2整除p-1
p-1, and indeed the gcd(2,p-1) is
not equal to 1, So this is not the easy case.
实际上2和p-1的最大公约数不等于1，所以，这不是一个简单的例子
So the algorithm that we just saw on
the previous slide is not gonna work when
所以我们前面看到的算法在这里不适用了，
we want to compute square roots modulo
an odd prime.
当我们想计算模奇数的平方根。
So when we work modulo odd prime, the squaring function is actually a
2-to-1 function. Namely, it maps X and
所以当我们计算模奇数时，这个平方函数实际是一个2对1的函数，即它
minus X to the same value. It matched both
of them to X squared. And as a result, we
它描述的是一个x和负x具有一样的值。它使得x和-x都与x平方相匹配，因此
say that this function is a 2-to-1
function. So here's a simple example.
我们说这个函数是2对1的函数，这里有一个简单的例子
Let's look at what happens when we compute
squares modulo eleven. So you can see that
它描述的是一个x和负x具有一样的值。它使得x和-x都与x平方相匹配，因此
1 and -1 modulo 11 both map
to 1. 2 and -2 both map to 4.
我们说这个函数是2对1的函数，这里有一个简单的例子
3 and -3  both map to
9, and so on and so forth, So you can
让我们看一下当我们计算平方数模11会出现什么情况。之后你就会
see that it's a 2-to-1 map. So, in
fact, these elements here, 1, 4,
明白1和-1模11都匹配1.2和-2都和4匹配
9, 5, 3, all are gonna have square roots. For example, the square root
3和-3都和9匹配等等，所以你会明白
of 4 is simply gonna be 2 and 9.
And I claim that, in fact, none of the
这是一个2对1的函数，实际上，这些元素，1，4，
other elements of Z11 are gonna have
a square root. And that motivates this
9，5，3都有平方根。例如，4的平方根
definition to say that an element x in ZP,
we're gonna say, is called a quadratic
是2，9的平方根是3.我想声明的是实际上
residue. If in fact, it has a square root
in ZP. Okay, and if it doesn't have a
Z11中其他元素中没有一个有平方根。这就促使了
square root, we'll say that it's a non
quadratic residue. For example modulo 11
这个定义，说在Zp中的一个元素x，我们刚说的被称作一个二次剩余
4 is going to be a quadratic
residue, 9 is a quadratic residue, 5
实际，它在Zp中有一个平方根。假设它没有平方根
is a quadratic residue, 3 is a
quadratic residue, and, of course, 1 is
我们就说它是非二次剩余。例如模11
a quadratic residue. So let me ask you, if
p is an odd prime, what do you think is
4就是一个二次剩余，9是二次剩余，
the number of quadratic residues in ZP?
And I'll give you a hint; the squaring
5是二次剩余，3是二次剩余，当然
function is a 2-to-1 map, which means
that half the elements in ZP can't have a
1也是二次剩余。好的我问一下，如果p是一个奇数，你认为
pre-image under this map. So the number of
quadratic residues is simply (p-1)/2 + 1
它是Zp中的一个二次剩余吗？好的我给你们一个暗示，
And the reason that's
true is because we know that exactly half
这个平方函数是一个2对1，这将意味着在Zp中一半的元素
the elements in ZP are gonna be
quadratic residues, Because of the fact
在这种映射下没有预映射。所以二次剩余的个数为(p-1)/2 + 1
that the squaring function is a 2-to-1
map. So there can be, at most (p-1)/2
这个正确的原因是因为我们已经确切的知道
elements in the image of that
map. So half the elements in ZP are
在Zp中一半的元素是二次剩余，由于
quadratic residues, And then, in ZP,
there's also zero. We also have to account
平方函数是2对1的映射这个事实，所以
for zero. Zero is always a quadratic
residue, 'cause zero squared is equal to
在这个函数映射中最多有(p-1)/2个元素，所以Zp中一半的元素是二次剩余
zero. So overall, we get (p-1)/2
quadratic residues in ZP, plus 1,
之后再Zp中也存在0，我们也必须考虑0
the zero element, which is a quadratic
residue in ZP. So overall, in ZP, there
0总是二次剩余，因为0的平方等于0
are (p-1)/2 + 1 quadratic
residues. Okay, so the main points to
好的，总而言之，在Zp中我们得到 (p-1)/2个二次剩余，加1，
remember is that roughly half the elements
have a square root and the other half does
元素0，它是Zp的一个二次剩余，总之，在Zp中
not have a square root. I wanna emphasize
that this is very different from the easy
有(p-1)/2 + 1 个二次剩余，好的这里应该记住的关键点是
case, where e was relatively prime to p-1. If you remember in the easy
大概一半的元素有平方根而一半元素没有
case, every element in ZP had an e'th
root. When e is not relatively prime to p-1,
我想强调的是这一点不同于简单事例。
that's no longer the case, and
in particular in the case of e equals 2,
简单事例中e和p-1是互素的。如果你还记得那个例子
only half of the elements in ZP have
a square root. Well, so the natural
在Zp中的每一个元素都有e次方根。当e与p-1是互素的
question then is, can we given an element x
that's in ZP, can we tell whether it has
不仅仅是那个例子，尤其当e=2时，
a square root or not? So Euler did some
important work on that too and in fact, he
在Zp中只有一半的元素有平方根，好的所以很自然的问题是
came up with a very clean criteria to test
exactly which elements are quadratic
给出一个Zp中的元素x，我们能分辨出它是否有平方根吗？
residues and which are not. And in
particular he said that x and ZP is a
欧拉在这方面做了很多研究，实际上
并且我们特别提到X和ZP是二次剩余，
residues and which are not. And in
particular he said that x and ZP is a
quadratic residue if and only if x to the
power of (p-1)/2 is equal to 1 modulo p.
他想出了一个非常清晰的准则来准确地测试元素是二次剩余
当且仅当X的(p-1)/2次幂等于 1 mod p的值。
quadratic residue if and only if x to the
power of (p-1)/2 is equal to 1 modulo p.
这是非常简单的情况，下面我们来看一个Z11中的例子。
Okay, very, very elegant and
very simple condition. Let's see a simple
也就是说我们计算模11的情况。
example in Z11, so when we work mod 11. So here I compute it at the 5th
我计算它在 11 中的所有元素的五次方，
power of all the elements in 11 for
you, and you can see that this symbol,
我们看到X乘以（p-1）/2，总是为1或减去1，
this X to the (p-1)/2, is
always either one or minus one, and it's
那么在二次剩余中我们可以精确到，1,3,5和9.
one precisely at the quadratic
residues--so 1, 3, 4, 5, and 9.
以上几个数就是二次剩余，剩下的元素不是二次剩余。
Okay, those are the quadratic
residues, and the other elements are not
我用绿色把它们圈起来。
quadratic residues. Here, I'll circle them
in green. These are the elements that do
这些是当我们对其做Mod11运算时没有平方根的数。
not have a square root when we work modulo
11. One thing I'd like to point out
我要特别讲一点，如果取不为零的X，我们看X(p-1)/2
is, in fact, if we take an x that's not
equal to 0, and we look at x to the (p-1)/2
我们可以将其写成x（p-1）的平方根
Well, we can write that as the square root of x to the p-1
The kind of, the half bubbles out, and this is simply the square
这就是x（p-1）的平方根。在费曼定理中x(p-1)就是1。
root of x to the p-1. Well, x to
the p-1 by Fermat's theorem, is 1.
因此是x（p-1)/2也就是1的平方根，也就是1或者-1。
So, x to the (p-1)/2 is
simply a square root of 1, which must be 1 or -1.
以上证明了这里的求幂运算一定会输出1或者-1.
So what this proves is that really this exponentiation here must
我们看到了证明的过程。
output 1 or -1, and we actually
saw that happening here. It outputs 1
当x为二次剩余是，会输出1.当x不是二次剩余时
when x is a quadratic residue, and it
outputs -1 when x is not a
输出-1。这不是一个很难的证明，在这里我们
quadratic residue. This is not a
particularly difficult proof, but I'm not
就不进行证明的演示了。证明会在这个模块结束时的作为参考给出。
going to show it to you here. It's in the
reference that I point to you at the end
为了讲解的完整性，我来讲讲这部分的计算。
of the module. And just for completeness,
I'll mention that this value, x to the (p-1)/2
我们给x（p-1）/2取个名字，称为x对p的拉格朗日标志。
has a name, it's called the Legendre's symbol of x over p.
正如前所说，在ZP中的元素标志为1或-1取决于
And as we said, this for elements in ZP the symbol is either 1 or -1
x是否为二次剩余。现在，欧拉定理有个不好的地方在于
depending on the quadratic residuosity
of x. Now, the sad thing about Euler's
它不是可构造的。尽管这是一个非常非常棒的定力。
Theorem is that it's not constructive.
Even though it's a very, very cute theorem,
它告诉我们哪些数是二次剩余，哪些不是
it tells us exactly which elements are quadratic residues and which
可是这个定理并不是可构造的。也就是说
aren't, this theorem doesn't do it
constructively, in the sense that if we
如果我们想计算一个二次剩余的平方根，定理不能
want to compute the square roots of a
quadratic residue, the theorem doesn't
确切地告诉我们该怎么做。还有，即使你想看证明，
actually tell us how to do that. And in
fact, even if you look at the proof, the
证明也是要基于确定存在的参数的。因此这个定理证明了平方根是存在的，
proof is by an existential argument. So it
proves that the square roots exists, but
但是并没告诉我们怎么计算平方根。
it doesn't show us how to compute the
square root when we want it.
所以下一个问题就是我们如何计算素数模的平方根。
So the next question is then how do we compute square roots modulo primes. So it turns out
这不是个困难的问题，我们将其拆分成两块来看。
that's actually not so hard and, again, it
breaks up into two cases. The first case
第一，当p等于3mod4，这时很容易计算平方根。
is when p is equal to 3 modulo 4
in, which case, it's really easy to
这是一个简单的函数。
compute the square root and I'll just tell
you there's a simple formula. The square
C的平方根就是C的（p+1）/4次幂。
root of c in this case is simply c to the
power of (p+1)/4.
你们会注意到因为p等于3mod4，
You'll notice that because p is equal to 3
modulo 4, p+1 is necessarily,
p+1等于0mod4，也就是说p+1可以被4除尽
p+1 is equal to 0 modulo 4.
Which means that p+1 is divisible by
因此(p+1)/4是整数。这也是我们可以计算这个求幂运算
4, and therefore (p+1)/4 is an integer. And that's exactly what allows
的根本原因。并且，这也告诉了我们C的平方根是什么。
us to compute this exponentiation, and I
claim that, that actually gives us the
通过很简单的函数，直接地可以求出C的平方根。
square root of c. Very simple formula,
that directly gives us the square root of c.
现在我们来证明它的真实性。
So let's verify that that's actually
true.
我们计算c的(p+1)/4词幂并求它的平方，
Well I'll take c to the power of (p+1)/4 and square that.
如果C的（P+1)/4次方是C的平方根，那么我上面做平方时应该会得到C。
And if, in fact, if c to the (p+1)/4 is the square root of c, when I square it, I should get c.
我们来看看会得到什么。首先，根据求幂运算的法则，可以得到等于C的（P+1)/2次幂。
So let's see that happens. So first of all, by laws of exponentiation, this is simply equal to c
我可以写下来C的f(p-1)/2次方乘以c
to the power of (p+1)/2. And that I can write as c to the power of (p-1)/2 times c
接下来，去除二分之一
Okay, again, this is basically, I took, one-half, and moved it
那么现在C的 (p-1)/2次幂怎么样了呢 ?
out of the exponentiation. Now, what do we
know about c to the power of (p-1)/2 ?
因为C是二次剩余，我们知道C的 (p-1)/2次幂是 1.
Since c is a quadratic residue,
we know that c to the power of (p-1)/2 is 1.
因此，上式也就等于1乘以C，也就是在ZP中我们
And therefore, this is really equal to one times c, which is c in
希望得到的C。因此我们证明了C的(P+1)/4次幂是C的平方根，
ZP as we wanted to show. Okay. So this
basically proves that c to the power of (p+1)/4
至少当p等于3模4时成立
is the square root of c, at least in the case when p is equal to 3 modulo 4.
现在可能有疑问，在什么情况下p等于1模4时？
Now you should ask me, well, what about the case when p is equal to 1 mod 4 ?
在这种情况下，这个公式甚至没什么意义
In that case, this formula doesn't even make sense. Because (p+1)/4
因为指数(p+1)/4不知道是否为一个有理分式
this exponent here, (p+1)/4 is gonna be a rational fraction, and I don't
我也不知道如何提高，c才能使其成为有理分式
know how to raise, c to the power of a
rational fraction. Nevertheless, it turns
然而它却说明了即使当p等于1模4时，我们可以高效地找到
out that even in the case where p is equal
to 1 mod 4; we can efficiently find
平方根，即使很难办到。特别是，我们并没有一个
square roots, although it's a little bit
harder. And in particular, we don't have a
处理它使用的确定性算法。我们得用随机化算法来得到
deterministic algorithm to do it. We have
to use a randomized algorithm to do it.
但是这种随机化算法实际上能高效地找到x模p的平方根
But this randomized algorithm will
actually find the square root of x mod p,
我猜我应该提过，如果有人可以证明
very efficiently. I guess I should mention
that if someone could prove that the
广义黎曼假设，这是一个很深奥的解析数论的假说
extended Riemann hypothesis--this is some deep
hypothesis of analytic number theory. If
如果有人能够证明这个假说是真的，事实上就得到了
someone could prove that, that hypothesis
is true, in fact, it would give a
甚至当p等于1模4时的一个计算平方根的确定性算法
deterministic algorithm for computing square roots even when p is equal to 1 modulo 4.
我之所以提起这个是因为
So the reason I like to mention that is because you notice that as
当你将计算透镜用在一些问题上时你就会发现了，比如
soon as you put the computational lens on
something--for example, I ask you to
要计算数x模p的平方根。就需要找到一个算法
compute the square roots of a number x
modulo p. Coming up with an algorithm
在数学上极其深入
already requires extremely, extremely deep
results in mathematics some of which are
有些甚至在今天都不知道是否是真的。照目前来看，我们不仅仅需要一个
not even known to be true today. So as
things stand today, we simply don't have a
确定性算法来计算p为1模4的平方根
deterministic algorithm to compute square
roots where p is 1 mod 4. But as I
但是我们有不错的随机化算法，这种问题就会变得容易
said, we have good randomized algorithms,
and this problem is considered easy.
本质上这可以归结为一些乘幂运算。结果就像我们看到的
Essentially, it boils down to a few exponentiations. And as a result, as we'll
计算平方根的时间本质上为p的比特数的立方
see, the running time of computing square
roots essentially is cubic in the number
非常完美。现在我们知道如何计算模p的平方根了
of bits of p. So excellence. And now we
know how to compute square roots mod p,
现在我们可以说说二次方程模p了
and so now we can talk about solving
quadratic equations modulo p. So suppose
假设我给一个二次方程让你用ZP找到解这个方程的方法
I give you a quadratic equation and I
asked you to find a solution of this
其实我想说你已经知道如何解决了
quadratic equation in ZP. Well so now I
claim that you know how to solve it. The
解它的方法基本上会使用你在高中解决二次方程的公式
way you would solve it is basically you
would use the high school formula for
所以解法是-b加减根号b平方减4ac
solving quadratic equations, you know. So
the solution is minus b plus minus the
我说你知道如何解
square root of b squared minus 4ac over
2a. And I claim that you know how to
这个公式里的所有元素。所以你就知道如何计算2a的倒数了
compute all the elements in this formula. So you know how to compute the inverse of 2a.
你可以用2a来划分。那么问题就利用扩展欧几里得算法得以解决
So you can divide by 2a. That's done using the extended Euclidean algorithm.
你也知道如何完成根号下b平方减4ac的计算，运用
And you know how to complete a square root of b squared minus 4ac, using one of
前面提到的平方根算法。当然这个公式
the square root algorithms from the
previous slide. And of course the formula
仅仅当平方根在ZP上实际存在时才可用
will only be solvable if the square root
actually exists in ZP. So that's cool. So
现在你们知道如何在ZP上解二次方根。那么下个问题是
now, you guys know how to solve quadratic
equations in ZP. So now, the next obvious
如何计算这些根的模合数二次剩余而不是模素数
question is what about computing these
roots, modulo composites rather than
我们可以问一个先前提过的相同问题
modulo primes. So we can ask exactly the
same questions that we asked before. So
什么时候e第i根模N存在?如果我们知道N存在
when does the e'th root modulo N exist?
And if we know that it exists, can we
我们可不可以更高效地计算出来?然而这个问题却非常困难
actually compute it efficiently? And here,
the problem is much, much, much harder.
事实上，计算e第i根复合模数
And in fact it turns out that, for all we
know, computing e'th roots modular
和对复合进行因式分解一样困难。对于一般情况下的e
composites is in fact as hard as factoring
that composite. Now, for a general e, this
我们现在能计算e的根模N的最好算法，虽然不知道是不是真的
is actually not known to be true, but the
best algorithm that we have for computing
需要我们把模数计入因子。一旦我们计入
e'th roots modulo N requires us to factor
the modulus. And once we factor the
那么就更容易计算e的原根中的每个素因子
modulus, then it's actually easier to
compute e'th roots modulo each of the
我们可以结合所有e第i根来得到e的模复合N
prime factors. And we can combine all the
e'th roots together to get the e'th roots
非常有趣的是，在计算e第i根
modulo the composite N. So it's a very
interesting case, where computing e'th
模素数就很容易了。事实上，对于很多e而言都是容易的
root modulo prime was very easy. In
fact, for many e's, it was very easy. But
但是计算e的根模复合数时时非常难的
computing e'th root  modulo composite is much, much, much harder and, in fact,
需要对N进行因式分解。这就是我想说的关于e第i根的问题
requires the factorization of N. So that's
all I wanted to tell you about e'th roots.
下节课，我们会说到模块化算法
In the next segment, we're gonna turn to
modular algorithms and we're gonna talk
将会讲到加法、乘法、乘方算法，模素数和复合
about addition and multiplication and exponentiation algorithms, modulo primes and composites.